Guide to the Alma Lutz Collection of English and American Women Authors, 1801-1876
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Alma Lutz Collection of English and American Women Authors
1801-1876
Lutz, Alma
0.4 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
A collection of handwritten letters, formal notes, autographs, poetry, short writings, and lithograph portraits of prominent nineteenth-century women authors, including Maria Edgeworth, Caroline L. Herschel, Hannah More, Lydia Huntley Sigourney, and Lady Emmeline Stuart Wortley.
Scope and Content Note
A collection of handwritten letters, formal notes, autographs, poetry, short writings, and lithograph portraits of prominent nineteenth-century women authors, including Maria Edgeworth, Camilla Toulmin Crosland, Caroline L. Herschel, Hannah More, Lydia Huntley Sigourney, and Lady Emmeline Stuart Wortley.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Crosland, Newton, Mrs., 1812-1895; Edgeworth, Maria, 1768-1849; Herschel, Caroline Lucretia, 1750-1848; More, Hannah, 1745-1833; Sigourney, L. H. (Lydia Howard), 1791-1865; Stuart-Wortley, Emmeline, Lady, 1806-1855
Subjects:
Women authors, American; Women authors, English; Women poets
Document Types:
Autographs; Correspondence; Lithographs; Poems
VCL Categories:
Autographs; Literature and Writing; Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, August 2007. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, April 2023.
Custodial History
A large portion (possibly all) of the collection was purchased by Alma Lutz from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Boston, in 1949.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alma Lutz (VC 1912), circa 1974.
Container List
- Abdy, Maria — Manuscript poems for The Forget-me-not and Keepsake, 1835-1863 (Folder 1.01)
- Abdy, Maria — Note to Miss [Camilla] Toulmin, 1841 (Folder 1.01)
- Aquilar, Grace — Note to Dr. Shelton MacKenzie, 1844 (Folder 1.02)
- Austin, Sarah — Note to Monsieur M. de Manotti, [1840?] (Folder 1.03)
- Baillie, Joanna — Letter to "My dear Sir Hampstead", undated (Folder 1.04)
- Baillie, Joanna — Lithograph of portrait by Sir W. Newton from Eclectic Magazine, undated (Folder 1.04)
- Barbauld, Anna Letitia — Letter to Miss Harris, undated (Folder 1.05)
- Blessington, Marguerite (Lady Blessington) — Lithograph of Grafin von Blessington, undated (Folder 1.06)
- Blessington, Marguerite (Lady Blessington) — Note to Miss Toulmin, 1825 Aug 16 (Folder 1.06)
- Busk, [Mary Margaret] (Mrs. William) — Manuscript poem, "The Savior of His Country", undated (Folder 1.07)
- Cappe, Catherine — Letter to a young friend, Miss Harris, York, 1812 Feb 25 (Folder 1.08)
- Cappe, Catherine — Lithograph, engraving by Woolnoth, 1823 Jul 1 (Folder 1.08)
- Carleton, Caroline — Manuscript poems, "A Song of Australia" and "The Song of Australia" (The Gawler prize poem), undated (Folder 1.09)
- Cayne, Charlotte — Manuscript poem, "The Anemone", undated (Folder 1.10)
- Cook, Eliza — Letter to Wiley & Putnam, from Ingress Abbey, Greenhithe, Kent, 1844 Mar 21 (Folder 1.11)
- Crawford, Mrs. — Manuscript poem, "The Day Dreamer", undated (Folder 1.12)
- Crosland, Camilla — Letter to J. P. Fields, 1852 May 31 (Folder 1.13)
- Crowe, Catherine Stevens — Formal note about her address in Edinburgh, [no year] [Aug 20?] (Folder 1.14)
- Dudley, Lady — Formal note from St. James Square, [no year] Apr 24 (Folder 1.15)
- Edgeworth, Maria — Part of a letter, signed, 1836 (Folder 1.16)
- Edgeworth, Maria — Signature on scrap of paper, undated (Folder 1.16)
- "Elizabeth" — Manuscript poem, "To My Sibyl’s Senses", undated (Folder 1.17)
- Fox, [Caroline] (niece of Charles James Fox) — Letter of introduction, 1808 Jul 6 (Folder 1.18)
- Garner, Theodosia — Manuscript poem, "On the Portrait of Her Majesty", undated (Folder 1.19)
- Godwin, Catherine Grace (Garnett) — Manuscript poem, "The Turkish Tomb", undated (Folder 1.20)
- Grant, Ann — Lithograph portrait, 1817 Jan 1 (Folder 1.21)
- Grant, Ann — Short note, undated (Folder 1.21)
- Hall, Anna Maria — Autograph stationary printed with The Rosery, Old Brompton, 1844 May 17 (Folder 1.22)
- Hall, Anna Maria — Letter to Miss Tomlinson, 1844 Apr 29 (Folder 1.22)
- Hemans, Felicia — Manuscript poem with note to Alaric A. Watts, Manchester, undated (Folder 1.23)
- Hemans, Felicia — Print illustration of a stone bust, undated (Folder 1.23)
- Hepney, Catherine — Manuscript poem, "Come Enjoy a Happy Sight", undated (Folder 1.24)
- Herschel, Caroline Lucretia — A leaf from her notebook, pasted on the back of an engraving of Hester Lynch Piozzi, undated (Folder 1.25)
- Hobbs, I. N. — Manuscript poem, "Lines Addressed to Richard Lane, the Sculptor, on Seeing the Statue of His Dead Child", undated (Folder 1.26)
- Hofland, Barbara — Letter to a young friend, undated (Folder 1.27)
- Hofland, Barbara — Manuscript poem, "On the Fine Arts", undated (Folder 1.27)
- Holmes, Mrs. Tom — Manuscript poem, "Italy", 1842 (Folder 1.28)
- Howitt, Mary — Letter to William, [no year] Jun 9 (Folder 1.29)
- Jersey, Lady — Formal note, [18?2] (Folder 1.30)
- Jewsberry, Geraldine Endsor (Mrs. Fletcher) — Manuscript poems, "The Paysanne in the City" and "A Lover’s Ballad", undated (Folder 1.31)
- Keating, Eliza H. — Manuscript poem, "Virginius and His Daughter", undated (Folder 1.32)
- L., M. A. — Manuscript poem, "Maid" for The Forget-me-not, 1828 (Folder 1.33)
- Lawrence, Hannah — Manuscript poems, "Swanhilda’s Song" and "The Dying Knight", undated (Folder 1.34)
- "Mariana" — Manuscript poem, "My Hope of Heaven", undated (Folder 1.35)
- Martineau, Harriet — Clipping, 1876 (Folder 1.36)
- Martineau, Harriet — Letter, signed, with transcript, 1835 Mar (Folder 1.36)
- Maur, Lady Charlotte S. — Manuscript poem, "Polish Martial Hymn", 1837 (Folder 1.37)
- More, Hannah — Lithograph of a painting of Wrington Church Yard and the grave of Hannah More, 1836 (Folder 1.38)
- More, Hannah — Lithograph portrait, undated (Folder 1.38)
- More, Hannah — Note about a payment of 660 pounds, Bath, 1801 Feb 18 (Folder 1.38)
- Morgan, H.C. (of Bangor) — Manuscript poem, "On the Death of Mrs. Cotton", 1823 Oct 12 (Folder 1.39)
- Morgan, H.C. (of Bangor) — Note about Mrs. Morgan and a print of her mother’s castle, Mettingham, Suffolk, undated (Folder 1.39)
- Morgan, Lady Sydney Owenson — Lithograph of a portrait by Berthon, 1825 Nov 1 (Folder 1.40)
- Morgan, Lady Sydney Owenson — Note to Lydia Meovrolli, undated (Folder 1.40)
- Morley, Countess of — Manuscript poem, "Epilogue", 1834 (Folder 1.41)
- Opie, Mrs. Amelia — Place card and autograph, undated (Folder 1.42)
- Pigott, Harriet — Letter to "Dear Sir", 1841 Aug 18 (Folder 1.43)
- Piozzi, Mrs. Hester Lynch — Lithograph of a drawing by J. Jackson, undated (Folder 1.25)
- Porter, Anna Maria — Lithograph of a portrait by G. H. Harlow, 1823 May 1 (Folder 1.44)
- Porter, Jane — Lithograph of a portrait by G. H. Harlow, 1815 Apr 1 (Folder 1.44)
- Porter, Jane — Note to Emerson, undated (Folder 1.44)
- Power, Anna Marsh — Manuscript poem, "The Mountain Child", 1842 (Folder 1.45)
- Power, Anna Marsh — Manuscript poems, "Lines on the Portrait of Miss Meyer", 1843 (Folder 1.45)
- St. John, Lady Isabel — Lithograph of a portrait by J. Hayter, undated (Folder 1.46)
- St. John, Lady Isabel — Manuscript poem, "Lines Written in a Book of Travellers in Italy", 1829 (Folder 1.46)
- Savage, Anna — Manuscript poem, "The Fairy King", 1843 (Folder 1.47)
- Sheridan, Louisa H. — Manuscript poem, "A Youthful Abbot", 1838 (Folder 1.48)
- Sigourney, Lydia Huntley — Manuscript of "Last Words of an Indian Chief", 1830 Jan 10 (Folder 1.49)
- Sigourney, Lydia Huntley — Note to Frederick Shobert, editor of The Forget-me-not, London, 1830 Jan 10 (Folder 1.49)
- Sinclair, Catherine — Letter to "Dear Madam" (probably Mrs. Greene, one of her readers in America (Mr. Green) mentioned), 1847 Sep 3 (Folder 1.50)
- Sinclair, Catherine — Calling card with "Cleopatra’s needle" written on it, undated (Folder 1.50)
- Smith, Lydia B. — Manuscript poems, "The Hero’s Sword" and "The Night Watch at Sea", 1836 (Folder 1.51)
- Sparrow, Alicia Jane — Manuscript poem, "Hannibal", 1843 (Folder 1.52)
- Thomas, Mrs. Edward — Manuscript poem, "Love", 1843 (Folder 1.53)
- Toulmin, Camilla (Mrs. Newton Crosland) — Letter to Dr. R. Shelton MacKenzie, undated (Folder 1.54)
- Toulmin, Camilla (Mrs. Newton Crosland) — Manuscript poem, "On the Fate of 'The President' Steamship," London, 1841 May 10 (Folder 1.54)
- Toulmin, Camilla (Mrs. Newton Crosland) — Leaflet, "Lays and Legends, illustrative of English Life," London: Jeremiah How, 1845 (Folder 1.54)
- Trollope, Frances — Note to Mrs. Gratten inviting Emma to Covent Garden, undated (Folder 1.55)
- Vernon, Honorable Caroline — Manuscript poem, "Goodbye and How D’y Do", undated (Folder 1.56)
- Victoire, Victoire — Manuscript poem, "Song", 1843 (Folder 1.57)
- Wilson, Margaret Harries (Mrs. Cornwell Baron Wilson) — Letter to Dr. Shelton MacKenzie, 1842 Mar 10 (Folder 1.58)
- Wilson, Margaret Harries (Mrs. Cornwell Baron Wilson) — Manuscript poem, "Poets Die in Autumn", undated (Folder 1.58)
- Wilson, Florence — Manuscript poem, "Flowers", 1843 (Folder 1.59)
- Wilson, Florence — Manuscript poem for Keepsake, "Stanzas", undated (Folder 1.59)
- Wortley, Lady Emmeline Stuart — Manuscript poem, 1842 (Folder 1.60)
- Wortley, Lady Emmeline Stuart — Manuscript poem, "Gypsy Children Caught in a Storm", undated (Folder 1.60)
- Wortley, Lady Emmeline Stuart — Manuscript poem, "Death and the Child", 1863 (Folder 1.60)
- Wortley, Lady Emmeline Stuart — Manuscript poem, "Lines on Haddon Hall", 1833 (Folder 1.60)
- Wortley, Lady Emmeline Stuart — Manuscript poem, "To a Lady in a Reverie", 1836 Aug 2 (Folder 1.60)
- Wortley, Lady Emmeline Stuart — Manuscript poem, "Song", 1863 (Folder 1.60)
- Wortley, Lady Emmeline Stuart — Manuscript poem, "On the Portrait of the Honorable Mrs. Craven", 1863 (Folder 1.60)
- Wyatt, Lady — Manuscript poem, "A Broken Heart", undated (Folder 1.61)
- Wyatt, Lady — Manuscript poem, "Ask Not If I’ve Loved Thee", 1862 (Folder 1.61)
- Youatt, Elizabeth — Letter to Mrs. Wilson, 1842 Mar 11 (Folder 1.62)
- Unsigned — Manuscript poem, "The Lament of a Quiet Gentleman Who Had Three Gay Daughters", undated (Folder 1.63)
- Unsorted cards name cards, undated (Folder 1.64)
- Unidentified lithograph portrait, undated (Folder 1.64)
- Card index to collection contents, undated (Folder 1.65)